Good afternoon.
I would like to call the meeting to
order. Welcome to the March 2nd public
service committee. We would ask the
public and staff to turn cell phones off
or to set them to vibrate and mute if
their devices are online. Um, if you
want to make a public comment online,
please use the raise hand function or um
approach the podium if you're here with
us in person and turn the microphone on.
You can just push the button. We would
ask the public and staff to clearly
identify yourselves uh for staff reports
and public comment and also there will
be no additional business discussed
following the completion of the agenda.
So, um, will the clerk read the first
agenda item?
>> Number seven, ordinance third reading,
creating chapter 8.72, private displays
on public property to prohibit the
unauthorized use of public property for
specified private displays.
>> Okay. And do we have a staff report?
Okay. up there.
Uh good afternoon, Madam Chairwoman.
David Hopinson,
deputy city attorney.
Uh this proposed ordinance just again
very briefly uh creates a new chapter
8.72 and provides some regulation and
guidance on the private uh for private
displays on public property. be happy to
answer any questions that any of you may
have with respect to the ordinance or
how it may work.
>> Okay. Do we does the committee have any
questions for the presenter?
>> All right. Um
and we'll go to public comment. Is there
any public comment on this? Okay.
>> That's all right.
Uh my name is Chelsea McCort. Um and I
am in Ward One. Um I wanted to briefly
touch on how
in general this whole
uh public display on private property
feels a lot like a personal agenda that
someone doesn't like how something looks
that's being pushed through as a city
level ordinance. Um there's a number of
different reasons. Number one, um I my
background is in anthropology. It is
really bad for culture when we criticize
how other people mourn and when we
remove opportunities that allow them to
mourn. Um it's disrespectful to the
people who have passed away. It's
disrespectful to the family and it truly
does destroy culture. Um there the issue
that keeps being brought up that it's a
safety concern is not actually true. um
studies 2019 2011 both show that uh the
presence of memorials does not affect
perceived risk and does not produce
clear systematic effects on travel
speed. There have been no recorded
documentations of people being hit when
visiting uh private memorials at least
in town. Um Y dot even has private
memorials along their roadside despite
having the Y DOT signs uh that that
option as well. um because it's not
really an issue. It's not a safety
issue. It's just that some people don't
necessarily like how they look or some
people don't like that it reminds them
of death. Um
the other thing I keep hearing brought
up is this Y dot sign being a possible
option. Um I know the district one
traffic engineer and read the um uh what
is it the the the paper that they put
out a brochure that's the word. Um and
basically that the white dot signs are
strictly for white dot road. So if
someone is hit on a public road dot will
not provide them with a sign uh city
sorry city road why dot will not prov
provide them with a a state sign even if
it's generally in the vicinity. Um as an
an alternative if the city wants to do
something like y dot know that y dot
operates that at a loss. It's a
financial burden for and additional work
for city employees and staff. Um, other
alternatives cost money. People don't
necessarily have it. The last thing
someone who is graving is going to be
thinking of is the fact that they need
to check their city code to see if
they're in violation. It's hard to know
who exactly put up the memorials. Um,
maybe you think it's the family member
and really it was a friend. So, there's
no regulations uh dictating or verifying
that. Fort Collins actually does have a
regulation with it. it is that they
allow the public memorials to be up for
30 sorry private memorials to be up for
30 days and that's only if they receive
a complaint. If not, they basically just
have said that they ignore that issue.
Um they do make amendments for like if
they're in front of a a fire uh fire
hydrant or other important things like
that, but generally speaking, it's not
an issue. Um and the fact that we're
trying to restrict it is just very rude
and insensitive.
>> Thank you, Miss McCort. Any
other speakers today?
>> Hopefully it's the only exercise I'll
get today. Um David Nicely 200
Waltershide.
Um if it's in order. Um, there's 996
pages of city code. I know that because
I've been reviewing it to see what we're
allowed to do on our farm.
There's lots of people in a culture
that's no longer or becoming more and
more or becoming less and less
self-governed.
There's lots of people doing lots of
things that they shouldn't be doing.
Um, even if
putting memorials on the road is
something that someone shouldn't be
doing,
is it really a problem
that should we should be spending time
addressing
and adding to the city code that's
already beyond the point where we can
manage it?
One scholar, legal scholar, did his
homework
and determined that
practically every American is guilty of
at least three felonies a day that he
doesn't even know he's guilty of,
including Supreme Court justices,
because of the
expansion of administrative law.
Um, again, I've I've urged you all to be
kind and respectful. I think kindness
says,
"Let it go." Um, Chelsea's made good
points in that. Um, the folks putting
out the memorials
probably wouldn't
if they knew that it was illegal.
But they're already in that sense
self-governed. Leave them alone.
Anyway, I I I just urge you again to be
kind um and try to lead by dealing with
real problems. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Nicely. Any other
comments?
Hi, I'm Anna. I'm a newer resident of
Cheyenne about a year and a half.
>> So, thank you for this opportunity to
speak. Um, as far as
this
um goes, personally, I think it is a bit
of a distraction to have memorials on
public roads with everything that we
have to pay attention to. TV screens in
our cars, the LED lights particularly at
night that can be blinding.
Um
I c it can be a distraction and
to acknowledge that everyone mourns
differently.
Um I think if there were some
limitations maybe like was stated
earlier 30 days or something. Um,
but then is that getting into overreach
as well? So, I don't know what the right
move is as far as this goes. But
personally, I find it almost a
distraction from what could otherwise be
just beautiful serenity. And I also
think that that is private. So, to have
it on public land
kind of goes against
the private and the public.
>> Thank you.
Any other comments in the room?
Jennifer, are there any comments online?
>> No. Okay. All right, then. I'm going to
close public comment. And do do we have
a motion? I would move to approve on
third and final reading.
>> Second.
>> Okay. Uh, Councilwoman Aldrich moved and
Councilman Lelay seconded.
>> I have an amendment, Chairwoman.
>> Oh, go ahead.
>> I would like to amend uh section C under
8.72.020
under prohibitions um from $750 to $50.
So it would read that any person
violating the provisions of this chapter
shall be subject to a fine not to exceed
$50 and any cost incurred by the city
for removal of the display.
>> Okay. Do we have Oh, would you like to
explain?
>> I would just like to say that was a
recommendation uh by a gentleman at the
council meeting on Monday night, Mr.
Love, and I wanted to carry that forward
after I had discussed it with him.
>> Okay. Do we have a second for that
amendment?
Okay. The amendment dies for lack of a
second.
So, we are back on
the um ordinance.
Is there any comments from the
committee?
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Um Chairwoman,
uh first and foremost, I wanted to
address that this is not a p any type of
a personal agenda that's being promoted
here. This was brought forward by a
constituent who felt that it was
important uh to bring it forward. Um
while some things may be considered to
be um less important for city municipal
code than other things, um I think that
um we need to be sensitive to um and
hear out all of our constituents, not
just those that might have what uh some
might consider larger issues than
others. Um, I also want to point out
that this is not based on just one
public display. Right now in in Ward 3,
we have several public displays um that
are memorials and recognizing that
people do mourn differently and that
that's important to a culture, which I
completely agree with, and that people
have different methods of mourning. Um,
we do provide a lot of opportunities for
families um that would like to
memorialize their loved ones, whether
it's planting a tree, whether it's uh
putting out a memorial bench. Um there
are lots of opportunities to do that. Um
my concern is that at um that we need to
make sure that whatever we're doing is
consistent um and that um everyone
understands what those parameters are
and that um if those memorials are
probably not the appropriate um it
should not appropriately take place
probably on um public rightway or um
city property that haven't been gone
through that memorial process. So, um,
for that reason, I would encourage my
colleagues to vote in support of this.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. I have a
question for the city attorney
and uh, my question is I heard uh,
Dr. Aldridge make a amendment here to
lower the possible fine in a case like
this. And my question is what is the
general uh fine and possible jail time
across our city code in all regards?
>> Madam Chairwoman, uh David Hopinson,
deputy city attorney. So, kind of by
default, uh, for when you're talking
about criminal offenses, you're looking
at a misdemeanor, six months in jail,
$750 fine, unless another punishment is
prescribed by the ordinance. Um, and so
in this case, right now, it would just
be a $750 fine had the amendment passed.
You know, should the committee have gone
that route, it would have just been a
$50.
>> Well, I think that answers my question.
The point being this is a matter of some
confusion
uh
generally when we talk about our city
code. I don't know uh when if ever
certainly not in any recollection I have
did anyone get six months in jail for
anything in this in our municipal court.
And the $750 I'm not I I don't I'm not
sure that might happen. But I think that
the the reason that we really shouldn't
we should reach a general understanding
about this. Do we want to have uh some
elements of the code have this as a
maximum fine and then other elements uh
depending on the circumstances? I mean
that's up to the judge and the judge has
that ability to look at the facts and
make a determination.
So really it's not um it when you read
the code and you you probably don't
understand exactly how it operates
generally um you might believe that
that's a really excessive amount of
money to ever talk about
but it is not invoked
and if we're going to change it I think
we need to change it universally
not bit by bit so that we are having
different uh amounts um for offenses
that probably
will never raise themselves to the level
that might be conceived here with uh
that kind of a serious um judgment and
sentence. But I I just wanted to
emphasize that this our code operates
that way and if it it basically is
across the board and it's there for a
reason and so I'm quite confident that
in the real world of Cheyenne Wyoming no
one is going to get that kind of a fine
for anything related to this. And
furthermore um Madame Chairman thank you
Mr. Hopkins. Um and furthermore, uh I
also want to note this is uh probably
the most personal
difficult issue
that
comes before us and I certainly didn't
expect this but when you look at the
situation and how this
number of memorials has grown and how
the the one in particular that I'm
referencing on Nation Way has become
essentially permanent
and is uh I believe those solar lights
work. I haven't been over there in the
uh night. Uh and that that also is an
area where we have a lot of danger. Um,
and I'm I it's a difficult situation in
terms of that uh traffic uh flow as it
relates to pedestrian crossings, but we
had a number of deaths there and maybe
we can come up with something better. I
think it's time we took a look at it.
But um really
this is an there's opportunities for uh
these memorials and when we see more and
more um it really is something that I
I'm quite confident
no one is going to get fined. No one's
going to go to jail.
But in that situation,
um, I believe that this ordinance is
appropriate. Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldridge. Uh, Chairwoman Emmens, I
just I just want to for people who may
not have the document in front of them,
the ordinance, proposed ordinance, is
that um I believe my colleague from W
one is uh referenced this in a
roundabout way that um it currently
reads that there shall um the fine would
not exceed $750. So, it gives the court
um a lot of leniency on making that
decision. And um I agree that we would
if ever see any fine incurred for this
um that that is not to exceed. So it
could be much less than that based on
whatever the court judge would um
advocate.
>> Thank you, Dr. Renie.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. I
I'm not going to belver this because you
all know, you know, I've spoken on the
last two um opportunities. I'm opposed
to it. I do realize that these just
don't bother me. I probably notice one
for the first time I see it and then
after that it becomes part of the
landscape and and it at least to me they
are not a distraction. But on the other
the other thing that bothers me is I
realize that if one person says
something there is probably many other
people that have the same sentiment.
They just haven't said anything. But
this has not been a burning issue within
the city or with the people I talked to.
So it seems to me like we're writing law
or changing law for essentially one
complainant and um and I don't know that
I that's appropriate. So I am still
going to be a no. Thank you madam
chairwoman.
>> Okay. Any other comments? Okay then
let's go ahead and vote. All those in
favor please signify by saying I.
>> Opposed? No
>> chairwoman.
>> Point of order. Madam Chairwoman,
the chair does get to vote if it under
Robert's rules of order if it affects
the outcome, which means you can vote to
create it to break a tie or create a
tie.
>> Thank you, Miss Dr. Renie. So, um, there
will be no recommend
based on the failure of the vote.
There'll be no recommendation for the
public service committee on this item at
the next meeting of the governing body.
Next item,
>> number eight, ordinance third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Shy classification for certain
land located north of Prairie Avenue,
east of Powderhouse Road, west of
Rutter, and south of Story Boulevard
from AG Agricultural to NR3 neighborhood
residential
high density.
>> Okay, do we have a staff report?
Madame Chair, Morgan Dennis, Planning
and Development. Um, this is just
reszoning so we can allow for a senior
housing development. Um, there have been
no changes and there have been no
comments from the public. Um, I stand
for questions. Okay. Do we have any
questions for staff?
All right. Do we have any public
comment?
Hey, do we have Oh, is there any online?
Thank you. Okay. Um, do we have a
motion?
>> I would move to approve on third and
final reading.
>> Second.
>> So, it's been moved by Dr. Aldrich,
seconded by Councilman uh Lebornne.
Um, do the committee have any comments
and then go I'm going to go ahead and
call for a vote. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And opposed?
Okay. Okay. The recommendation for the
public service committee will be to
adopt on third and final reading.
>> Number nine, ordinance third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located
southeast of the intersection of South
Gley Highway and East Asia Lane from AG
agricultural to BP business park.
>> Thank you. And do we have a staff
report?
Chair, members of this committee, Conor
Way, Planning and Development
Department. Uh, this zone change is
basically an expansion of Bison and
Business Park. Uh, it is on third
reading. There's been no changes, no
public comment. I'm available for any
questions.
>> We do have any questions for staff.
>> Okay. Do we have any public comment?
>> Do we have any online?
Okay.
So committee, do you have any comments?
Do we have a motion to move forward?
>> I would move to approve on third and
final reading.
>> So it's been uh moved by Dr. Aldridge,
seconded by Dr. Renie.
Uh all those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
Okay.
Number 10, ordinance third reading.
Annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, various tracks of land
completely surrounded by current city
limits. Situate in western and southern
Cheyenne generally located east of I25,
south of the intersection of Westland
Road and Missile Drive, north of west
and east Allison Road, and east of and
adjacent to North College Drive. Okay.
Step report.
chair, member of the committee, Charles
Bloom playing and development director.
This is something we did email back
earlier in February on the 11th. This is
uh we have determined that
the urban farm classification fits into
the existing land uses. I should note in
our unified development code our uses
are very broad. So for example we do not
have a definition for church. It falls
into place of assembly. We don't have a
specific use for you know card shop or
bicycle shop falls into general retail.
So what this is
is this is basically the clarification
that the urban farm use that that is
something that falls into multiple
categories that are agriculturally
related and that they are permissible
within that zone district. Um the intent
is to give the nicely when they move
forward the ability to have a guarantee
that this land use is something that is
allowed in that agricultural zone
district. So just wanted to make sure
you all had this. Again, it has not
changed since the first time you have
seen it.
First I would like to start off. This is
third reading. Um as Connor would have
started before he mentioned this is we
have not received any further comment
from anybody regarding this annexation
for the seven county pockets that are
proposed with this city initiated
annexation. Um, since this time we have
had some conversations with the folks
out on the parcel that's zoned
agricultural out on Callis Drive. Um,
they sat down with myself, uh, with the
mayor, with Amber, and we had discussion
about how this affected them and we
talked to them about their future plans.
Uh, they did indicate they would love to
stay in the unincorporated county. Um,
but they did understand that there's a
path forward for their business. So I
would let any formal recommendation or
or comment from them come from them at a
future public meeting date. Um want to
provide a little bit of background just
on
the questions that we have um been
working on collectively as staff. Um
first of all, chief of staff Amber Ash
has done a really good job of uh
coordinating this with everybody. We've
had multiple individuals from multiple
departments um together working on
these. Um, initially there was the draft
uh 60
just 60-ish questions that came out and
then uh two Fridays ago we had one that
had 143 questions which was uh was more
finalized and then um on Friday four
more were added on. Uh those answers
were emailed um out to the uh the nicely
and also members of council um just
after 10:00 today after we did some
final looks on it. other variety of
variety of questions um that are across
the board. Um it was eye openening to
read the questions because it gave a
little bit more insight as to what was
going on on site. At first we really
thought well this is just a small
operation. Um not much is occurring and
opened our eyes up to just there's a lot
more things that are going on. Um it's
more than just what was approved by the
county which is a home occupation for a
400 ft farm stand. um and a farming
operation that doesn't exceed 25
customers daily.
Uh what we are looking to bring into the
city today is that exact use that was
approved by the county planning office
in 2021.
And then we've paved the path for them
to move forward in the future with what
is being referenced as an urban farm
which falls into these few land use
categories. these land uses. So, it
gives them a path forward to essentially
submit a site plan application for a fee
of $100, our cheapest application fee we
have just simply to document what they
are what they are doing and any
expansion and use and then we can
continue to work from there. they can uh
submit the land use documentation form
which is what we've asked um every
person who's being annexed by city
action to do which essentially allows
them to establish a site plan very
similar to this $100 site plan a nice
sketch something you'd be proud to turn
into your eighth grade teacher um you
can turn that in and that establishes
your site plan and that has no cost that
is included in the questionnaire
the county's approval back in 2021 one
uh that one was for home occupation and
it did say if it exceeded 25 customers
per day a site plan would be required.
Well, what is a a site plan in the
county look like? Um one of the more
recent ones we've had in the county and
we had the exact opposite with one in
the city. Um so we this works both ways
is the new McDonald's that was
constructed on South Gley Highway about
a stones throw to the east of this
actual property itself. Jefferson Road
is in the city limits. The McDonald's is
in the unincorporated county limits.
The applicant would for McDonald's had
to submit a county site plan which has a
bunch of unknown fees. First has a $500
base fee. Then it has a per uh signage
fee for notification. Has mailing fees
to neighbors. It has a legal ad fee. It
also has a unknown third-party review
fee
uh for a thirdparty engineer to look at
the application and then it also has um
fees by environmental health uh just for
looking at the site plan. Our
environmental health fees are only
related to the subdivision process, not
site plans. So, it's it's a little bit
more for a county site plan application
just to get started. And in addition,
then they have to file a second
application with the city because we're
looking at our access permit. In the
McDonald's case, it was for Jefferson.
In this case, it would be for
Waltershide to review the access, to
review what's proposed, where street
trees would be, those types of items.
So, in the long run, uh, I believe it's
fair to say the annexation would be
removing one procedural step that would
likely be required by the county in the
event of expansion because if they're
exceeding the 25 customers per day,
then they would be pushed into the site
plan. We don't know what their numbers
are today. We don't know if they exceed
25,
but they they could, maybe they don't.
Um, one more item to note is this
annexation as well as all annexations
for our county pockets were funded by
that 2022 city council goal where we
budgeted money to map and zone and take
care of all the costs associated with
these annexations. Uh, that can be
fairly expensive for the individual
property owner.
As the council is aware, and we've
talked about this a lot with throughout
the public hearings, is we have this
agreement between the city, the county,
and city county health, that is EPA
mandated that says if you have a septic
system and it fails within certain areas
surrounding the city, including the
islands, you are required to
connect to city sewer.
Um, you are able to go through a
variance process if you wish, which has
a fee. I believe the fees are, gosh, I
should have had those here. It's about
$1,200. You have a city fee and a board
of public utilities fee for the water
element if you choose to connect to
water. But you do have a fee that's
involved and it essentially looks at is
it financially feasible to connect to
city sewer. If it is, you'd be required
to connect and you'd also then be
required to annex as part of that
condition. And those annexation fees,
the mapping, the application fee, the
zoning, all of that would fall on the
landowner. Um, so
in the event that a septic system is
either modified, um, because maybe
they're adding another bedroom and once
you add another bedroom to a residence,
you change your septic system, you're
going to be brought up to a 2011 process
where you could be required to annex on
your own dime. If you connect, say, a
business to your existing septic system
that was designed for a residence,
same thing happens. If you bring in
another residential structure
and you go through the processes to get
a certificate of occupancy, you you
connect it to electric, you connect it
to water and sewer like that. Again,
that's going to trigger another review
by city county health. Um so in the end
what I really wanted to state is um
there are a lot of uh potential
we we've done a lot to ensure that this
path forward has been easy for the
nicely and is going to be predictable so
they know what is going to occur in the
future. But the biggest concern is
incorporation of this area is almost
assumed because septic systems don't
last forever. If you're not able to
expand a septic, replace a septic
system, you're going the property owners
will have to be brought on the NC limits
that way. And this is helping them set
the stage for a successful business in
the future. And there has been a
misconception that I've heard out here
that people are equating annexation to
eminent domain. Uh just over the weekend
I heard someone say and I saw a post on
social media where it says that
annexation
will result in the nicely having to stop
farming and give their property to the
city. That is not the case. There will
be no land conveyance. We will not be
acquiring any property. they will be
able to continue to farm and sell their
retail sales in their food stand as it
is today.
We are accepting of how these structures
have been developed in the county. We
don't know exactly how they have been
constructed in the county. Um, some have
electrical which weren't on their plans.
Others have other utilities that weren't
on their plans. They're lacking ADA
parking which is a federal requirement.
But those are items we're willing to
accept because they went through the
county approval process. And in the
future, we will work to evaluate what
requirements would be necessary as they
expand their use. Probably the bare
minimum is going to be to make sure that
that one parking space out front that's
reserved for the ADA, that that one is
paved and meets ADA standards because
that's that's a requirement in the city
and the county. You'll see it in almost
any gravel parking lot you go to in a
county development. You'll see that one
paved spot in the middle of a gravel
parking area. I'll use Pine Blast
Distillery as an example. They have a
paved parking space for ADA. We have one
at East Park on Persing. That's the bare
minimum and that's likely what you'd
expect with this type of development as
it moves forward through our process.
I'm open for any questions that you have
regarding this this item.
>> Are there questions? Dr. Renie.
>> Madam Chairwoman. Thank you.
Um, Director Bloom, on the note you
handed out that definitions.
Um, first, thank you. It's nice to know
that we do have a definition of urban
farm. It's been alleged that we did not,
but on agricultural product sales last
three lines
where it says, however, the intensity
and frequency of such sales shall be so
that no additional parking road
structures etc.
are necessary. Can you explain the what
that means for the impact of that?
>> I've got to highlight it if it's easier
to find it.
>> Chair, members of committee, uh through
you to Dr. Dr. Winnie. Uh this that's a
great question. The three definitions on
top are the ones that exist in our
unified development code right now.
Surprisingly, the agricultural project
sales/farmers market is one that's
identified in our definitions, but it's
actually not in the use table. Um, so
it's one that we use for guidance, but
what this is really geared at is looking
at those large operations where folks
would be selling machinery, large items
where you'd have auctions and and other
uh things occurring that would attract a
lot of folks. This uh is not intended to
apply to incidental sales.
>> Okay. Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. One
more question if I may. So, as I said,
I'm grateful that we have an urban farm
definition now. And my understanding is
that you were able administratively to
incorporate this into our unified
development code. Is that accurate?
>> Go ahead,
>> chair. Three to Dr. Rey, members of the
committee. This is incorporated as an
implementation like policy statement.
It's not officially in the unified
development code. Essentially what we do
is we allow these to go for a test drive
their official policy statement on our
website. We will utilize them. Um and
then if there are any growing pains or
issues that we see with it, we can work
with folks identify those issues to
tweak it. Then we bring it into the
development code. So it will be a future
zoning amendment. But this basically
says
this is how the urban farm use fits into
our current definitions and land uses
that we have today.
>> Dr. R.
>> So then essentially
we're test driving this and we'll
probably see it what January whenever we
annually bring up changes to the UDC. Is
that am I understanding that
>> chair through Dr. Rain and the
committee? Yes. You'll probably see it
even sooner than that because last uh
two Tuesday two Tuesday two Tuesday two
Tuesday two Tuesday two Tuesday two
Tuesday two Tuesday two Tuesdays ago the
planning commission met at their midmon
February meeting where they identified
they wanted to see this definition as
one of the unified development code
updates that we bring forward to you
relatively soon. So it is on this year's
work plan. Um this came up between the
time we had the work session with the
city council that Friday and the midmon
meeting. So they directed us to move
forward with that and we're working on
getting that started as we speak.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> uh, Chairwoman for you. So,
um, Mr. Bloom. My that is my
understanding also that this is while
this may be a guidance document that it
has the cotification of this would
happen at the next UDC
um zoning changes that we're going to be
that will be proposed and we'll be
working on um and you you believe that
that would be codified by July August
>> chair three the members of committee.
Um, we're hoping to have this drafted up
for public review and and sent to the
planning commission and governing body
as soon as possible because it's really
been diverting a lot of our staff
resources to this that's been delaying a
lot of our projects we've been trying to
work on, including the comprehensive
plan update. So, there's a lot of
projects that have had to take a
backseat. So, we would like to get this
out the door as quick as possible to
have some type of uh certainty for
everybody.
Are do you believe that you could
definitely have it codified within 12
months?
>> Three to Dr. Aldridge. Definitely.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Other questions for Mr. Bloom.
>> Okay. Then we'll go out for public
comment.
Long walk again. Um members of the
council, city staff, supporters, um
I'm here today um a little surprised
that
the process has been characterized by
Mr. Bloom as easy.
It could have been easy.
Um it hasn't been easy.
Um, I'm a little surprised that an
annexation was started on a farm
with no idea what we were doing.
For 400 years, my Amish ancestors
have been in Lancaster County doing what
we're doing without asking for
permission to live their lives and to
grow their food and to sell their crops.
We're not doing anything
dramatic,
strange,
abnormal.
There's
Well, they show up at our farm stand.
People
practically every day who've moved to
Cheyenne to do what we're doing.
We're homesteading
and
people want the freedom of homesteading.
As I said before, there's 996 pages of
city code.
I honestly,
as much as Mr. Bloom was was talking, I
think he was trying to persuade me to be
in favor of the annexation. And
if I looked at it as
it's normal and acceptable to be swamped
with an administrative boondoggle to
just live your life,
then I might be thankful. But
honestly, we got chickens and then we
got more chickens
and then we had a cow and then we had
sheep and my son wanted more sheep.
We built a greenhouse and we grew some
things and we built another one and we
built another one and then we sold some
stuff at the base of the drive. My my
children held up fresh egg signs and
danced and people bought them and then
we got a farm stand because the
government closed down the farmers
market.
What we're doing is normal. Um, and we
shouldn't have to fill out
an abysmal amount of paperwork to do it.
And we shouldn't live under the threat
that we can be closed down because we
grow.
Um,
you know,
Miss Edmonds, you you you wrote in a in
a kind Facebook post at the beginning of
this that I don't know whether you said
nothing was going to change, but you
said very little would change. From our
perspective, everything has changed
because we live without fear of the
government.
Now we're reading 996 pages of code and
we've hired an attorney. Not I don't do
that every day. I don't keep one on
retainer. I don't want to.
Um and we're talking about just selling
and going on to a place where we're
welcome because you know what?
I reached out to city council people in
January and got no response. Throughout
the process in month and a half, one
city councilman
just yesterday was kind and empathetic.
Two or three others of you have been
kind and empathetic in the process, but
I was we were slandered at the last city
council meeting.
>> Mr. I am not out of order.
>> No, I'm not saying you're out of order,
but you are out of time, sir.
>> I'm out of time.
>> Thank you, though.
Miss McCort.
>> Yes,
>> Chelsea McCort again. Um, so I have a
lot to say and hopefully I can get
through it all. Uh, three minutes is not
a lot, but um, firstly I did want to
make a comment in regards to the
budgeting and things in preparation for
the annexation. Um, if that was being
done, which it was done obviously, um,
there should have been some due
diligence in understanding perhaps some
of the nuance of the property of the
annexation things ahead of time. for
instance, this particular property,
parcel 4, um because there's a lot more
that goes on on it and it's kind of a
special case and I feel like that should
have happened before. It's like you're
running a little bit too fast and need
to take a step back and look. Um I do
want to make one quick regards to uh um
Bloom's comment about the social media
post. I want to make it clear that was
not us that was saying anything like
that just in case there was any question
about that. Um and we do definitely
appreciate the questions being answered.
Uh obviously if we are going to be
annexed we want to make sure that we are
complying. We want to do the best we
can. Um but the problem is that okay up
to this point we've say been saying we
don't think we'll be able to function
and we would like help verifying that.
And by function I mean function as
currently with with no changes or or no
significant changes. um we've received
the answers and now that we're looking
through the answers, we're seeing that
we are going to change and that that we
were concerned for a rightful reason. Um
just just looking at this I I only spent
five minutes reviewing it and I already
have five questions that I pulled up
that are problematic, that are in
congruent with how urban agriculture
functions. Um I don't know if I have
time to get into that specifically
because a few other comments that I
think are really important. um the urban
farm definition that uh Bloom presented
to you. We do appreciate we really
appreciate that you guys have started to
work on that process. And we appreciate
his time and the city's time. Um once
again, I reiterate that this is not an
emergency level of like we need to annex
or the world's going to end. So the fact
that they're diverting all these
supplies just to us seems unnecessary
when we could just slow the process down
and take the time and not demand things
instantly being done right away. We
aren't demanding that. We're just asking
that eventually we get the questions and
that we get it answered correctly and
that the the questions that are answered
that are in congruent that we find a
compromise whether that compromise is on
us how we're changing the practices or
if the compromise is changing or
altering city code as they currently
are. Um there are some issues within
that definition that were provided that
we would like to do commentary on. Um,
we haven't really had time to do that
though because we've been going back and
forth with all these questions. And so,
it's not that we don't want to do them
or we haven't been trying to do them. We
just have so many things we have to do
all at once because again, the deadline
is so tight. And so, that's the most
stressful part is um we just we just
need some sort of more time,
postponement, some sort of date
certified. I'm not exactly sure what the
best answer is. That's kind of up for
you guys to decide, but the way things
are, it just isn't going to work. We
have the questions, but now we have to
adapt to what the answers are.
>> Thank you, Miss McC.
>> Thank you,
>> Mrs. Nicely.
>> Hi. Um, I just find that the irony of
three minutes when this has longl
lasting
effects of how I'm going to farm, I only
have three minutes to do my case. Um, is
unfair and it's unjust. Um,
we've given you guys reasons why this
needs to be slowed down. Um
there is no time to respond if you guys
continue to go through the 9th. Um we
received notice from the city that the
fences will not be done by the 9th. You
guys are leaving my livelihood
vulnerable. Um I'm asking you please. Um
even the fact I don't think we should be
annexed until it is codified. um we
haven't been able to really work
with the parameters of what an urban
farm is now being proposed. Um I'm
thankful that Charles Bloom has done
some work and done that. I'm even more
thankful that he brought it to the city
council's
attention that we should look at
changing zoning violations to a civil
offense and not a criminal offense. Um,
personally, I think that should have
been dealt with before we were force
annexing anybody. Um,
I understand you guys haven't done a
$750 fine and six months in jail. I
don't want that hanging over me. I don't
think you'd want that hanging over you.
Um,
I I mean, we haven't even had time to
look over all the answers, but but
looking over them, I can't do turkeys
now. Um, it says I can't butcher them.
Um, I mean, there's all sorts of things
that we need to sit down and and it's
going to take more than three minutes.
Um,
I just wish you guys would work with us
and sit down and go through things. I'm
not expecting you guys to be farmers or
understand about herb and agriculture,
but I do think there is a positive way
forward. Um,
I'm convinced it can't happen by March
9th and I feel like we've wasted way too
much time to get to this point. Um,
again,
I don't think the city's ready
um to encompass and allow an urban farm
to operate within your parameters.
Just please
stop.
And I have 10 seconds.
Thank you, Mrs. Nicely.
Is there anyone else in the room that
would like to comment?
Good afternoon. Gay Woodhouse, 1912
Capitol Avenue, Sweet 500. Uh, I am
representing Wresh Farms at this point.
I was hoping that we would have answers,
you know, later in the week. Last week,
I'm no mayor. Colin said there was a
draft already being worked on and um
maybe we'd get it Wednesday last week,
but I do understand how many people have
to review it and have to make sure that
it says what you really mean. So I
appreciate that, but we know we just got
it and I actually didn't see it till I
got to this meeting. So I I believe that
to some extent, you know, we can
cintilate or assimilate our problems.
you know what what I've even seen just
reading it while we were talking before
a few things that just didn't seem
consistent and I don't know enough about
what's going on why fresh myself to say
does this matter or not so those are the
kinds of things I was really hoping that
we'd be able to come today and maybe
just you know bring those up but now
we're g we'll go through them we will go
through them and study them carefully
and you know it has been sort have
intimated that 143 questions plus four
is too many. But, you know, when you
think about people's livelihood, their
dreams, and what they've had for goals,
you know, in their life, it's not that
much. And and they were broken down by
category. They weren't just willy-nilly
rambling questions. They were
articulate. They were well written. They
each one sort of uh
improved on the last one. And sometimes
you answered the question, you know,
this we've referenced this in the two
pre the answer was we've referenced this
in the pre previous two questions, but
which I appreciate too. At least we know
that. And you do know a lot more about
what their their farm is all about,
which I might have said don't tell them,
you know, just don't tell them. We'll
get inex, we'll just do it. But now they
have been so honest and made themselves
vulnerable by telling you exactly what
their operation is about and what they
expect and what they hope to be able to
achieve.
So I'm I really hope that on Monday
night we will come with some more
questions. Hopefully we'll get some
answers to the ones we have pro from
this uh exchange here. But I um I have
to say too that it's 25 a day. You know,
why can't that be an average? I mean,
that sounds like somebody with a clicker
can be sitting outside
and go, "Oh, they had 26. Let's go in.
Let's make them do stuff." I mean, we
know in the summertime they're going to
have a lot more people than they will in
the winter time. And they have probably
days when they get four customers. I'm
not sure, but you know, the 25 as just a
straight 25 a day just seems
unreasonable. So, that's just my only
comment. I'm done. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Uh, Miss Woodhouse, I also
want to say that that 25 a day is a
county rule, not a city rule. So, that's
>> that's part of their permit.
>> Yeah.
>> But we're now we're going to be in the
city.
>> Madame Chairwoman, mayor.
>> Dr. Renie
>> council, I was going to ask I wanted to
ask you that since you brought it up. My
understanding is part of their permit
through the county is that they are
limited to 25 patrons a day and it it's
not necessarily customers. If a family
of five walks in, that takes up 20% of
their aotment.
So to me, it would seem that that
requirement will not be there when
when they're annexed into the city. It's
a county requirement. I assume they're
complying with that and I, you know, as
a former commissioner, I would think
that you would want them complying with
the county regulation.
Um, but to me it seems like if with
annexation that would no longer apply
and they would actually be able to
expand their business as they claim they
as they claim they plan to.
>> Madam Chairman, through you I I saw
something in the answers that I was
reading that still made it sound like
that still might be the 25. Okay. Well,
we can address that on our end.
>> Thank you.
>> Um,
>> Madam Chairwoman, if I may, um, and I'll
since Miss Woodhouse, you're
representing them, I'll direct my
questions to you. But it's been um it
was stated that if they have to in if
they increase the number of their
livestock or chickens and and that they
would have to expand a barn or a um
chicken coupe or one of their
outuildings that they would now be
required to get a city building permit,
which they would, but currently they're
required to get a county building
permit, aren't they?
>> Madam Chairman, through you I'm not
sure.
>> Okay. Well, I think that's something. Um
I think they are and somebody can
correct me if I'm wrong on that, but to
me I don't see a change there. Um they
are protected by the um in the county
they're protected
in the answers, but with growing their
own produce and animals and selling that
they're protected by the Wyoming Food
Freedom Act. That applies whether
they're in the county or the city.
Correct
>> madam chairman through you. Yes.
>> So again that's nothing about that part
of their operation is going to change.
Um there was a gentleman that said that
appreciated the fact that they were
dispersing
um or distributing helping him to
distribute his beef products. That's
regulated by the state board of
agriculture and that applies whether
they're in the city or the county. We
have no control of that. Correct
>> madam chairman through you. I believe
that's correct.
>> Okay. So again that part of their
operation I mean so when I look at some
of the the parts of their operation that
are um
being in the being in the city doesn't
change because those are regulated in
other areas. So to me it's like there
will be some changes but mostly it's
just a change in the color on the map.
But thank you madam chairwoman.
>> Thank you. Thank you.
>> I just wanted to make a note that in the
county there is exemptions for a
buildings. There's some requirements
within that. Um, and that appears to be
changing if we're
annexed into the city, which will put
another financial burden on our farm.
Thank you, Miss Nicely. Other comments.
Hi, Andoma again. Um,
I just wonder
spending this amount of time and money
and effort into annexing
properties
when I see a lot of roads in Cheyenne
that really need attention that could be
quite dangerous to the residents. So I
look at things as if you have a strong
foundation then at that point
I it's gives you the freedom to expand
when there are things internally that
need to be addressed address those make
them strong
and then move forward with that
strength.
So,
I just wonder if this is
I can't think of the there's a fun
anecdote like the putting the horse
before the cart or the cart before the
horse kind of thing.
So, I just wanted to say that. Thank
you.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment in
the room?
Hey, Jennifer, do we have public comment
online?
Okay, then I'm going to close public
comment.
Okay, committee.
Dr. Renie.
>> Oh, I did leave my light on, didn't I?
All right, Madam Chairman, I would move
to approve on
>> Okay. Uh,
>> second.
>> Chairwoman Emmens, I would move to
amend.
Go ahead, Dr. Aldridge.
>> Um, I would like to amend this um
annexation
to and I'm sure the city attorneys are
going to need to help with this wording,
but um I would like to move forward with
parcels 2, three, four, five, and six um
and the um
seventh parcel and the fourth parcel. I
would like to amend this ordinance uh
proposed uh annexation to uh have a date
certain for those two parcels um one
year from u March 9th. So March 9th of
2027 which would allow us to
can I explain why?
>> Yes.
>> Thank you. uh which would allow us to
make sure that the fence is repaired, to
make sure that the urban farm is
codified, and to have all of these other
uh time to work through all of these
other questions that have been proposed.
As I was um reading through here, I
think that there were Thank you to the
staff that did a a a monumental lift of
answering these questions, but there are
some questions that um I think uh remain
if not by the owners of the farm um by
perhaps some of us on the council about
some of the comments that were made in
these responses. And I understand that
there are some additional questions that
have been submitted that um are not
included in these responses. Um there
were not any additional questions
in
>> Oh, they're in here now. Okay. Um so, um
I would like to make that amendment.
>> Dr. Aldrich, can you repeat the
amendment?
>> Yes. That we would uh approve on third
and final reading, uh parcels 2, 3,
four, five, six um for annexation um
effective um whenever the mayor signs
the final ordinance. is approved and
that this would be effective one year
following that date. Um so that we have
time to work with parcels four and seven
to make sure everything is finalized and
codified um and their fences repaired
before um we move forward at that. I
mean with that just in clear
transparency that would mean in one year
that the farm and parcel 7 would be
annexed um without um any further um
public notification or anything like
that. It would just happen one year from
whatever that date is. So
>> Dr. Aldrich I need to get some
clarification. So are you saying that
seven and four would not be annexed at
this time?
>> Correct. and
>> they would be one year from they would
be date certain
>> and you are remembering that two of the
parcels in seven are willing to go
forward now.
>> Yes,
>> Madam Chairman. Yes.
>> Just one quick question. In in both
cases, Dr. Alder's not included parcel
number one. Are you intending to include
parcel number one?
>> I'm sorry. One would be annex now.
>> Okay. I just want to thank you for
catching that.
>> Councilman's Labour,
did you have a comment?
>> Oh, do we have a second?
>> Um, I second for the purpose of
discussion.
>> And I think our attorneys, we have some
questions for the attorney.
>> I do.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> Madam Chairwoman, to council. I guess I
want his opinion, but it seems to me
that
I don't know. It seems to me like if we
start dividing things and applying rules
differently
to if we start applying our ordinances
differently to different individuals or
different parcels.
um that could
potentially create a an instance where
we could be accused of showing
partiality or not applying our
ordinances uniformly. Is that possible?
>> Go ahead,
>> Madam Chairwoman. John Brody, city
attorney.
To Dr. Renie, I I guess I mean it does
establish a policy precedent, right? I
mean, it it deviates from the previous
nine county pocket ordinances that this
council has considered and approved. Um,
you know, from a legal perspective, I I
I think I have some other um issues that
we've kind of identified as um we've
explored this issue since it first came
up on Monday. Um, for example, the the
ordinance that sort of speaks to the
effective date of annexations doesn't
speak in the context of multiple
effective dates. It speaks in the
context of an ordinance having a
effective date. Um, which um, you know,
state statute isn't clear. I think we
all can um, appreciate that. Um, but if
you read it strictly, you know, there
there are certainly concerns from my
office and I've had conversations with
the planning department on whether or
not a split effective date is
appropriate under these circumstances.
Um, my advice candidly would be if if
the intent is to delay um then you just
simply delay the entire ordinance and
not um split it into parcels. Um, we
also have concerns
um from an administrative standpoint. Uh
we've city staff have had conversations
with the city surveyor with regard to
the myars that would have to be
prepared. Um having multiple myars or
sort of footnotes inserted into myars as
to different portions of the city um and
when they became part of the city from a
jurisdiction aspect. Um it does not
adhere to really best practices at least
from the surveyor's perspective. Um so
there's there's a lot of complications I
think that this approach raises. I'm not
saying you can't do it. Um, but city
staff has had enough time to kind of
think about it and and coordinate and
um, you know, there there are some some
concerns about it. Um, I hope that
answered your question, but I'm happy to
answer others.
>> Thank you, Dr. Mr. Brody. Dr. Aldrich,
>> I have a question. Chairwoman Emmens for
you. Um I know that we have invested a
lot of money into the surveying and the
annexation process um for all of these
annexations not just this one.
Um my desire with the date certain was
that we would be able to preserve some
of that taxpayer money that has already
been expended.
I am sure that our surveyor or any
surveyor would um like to be paid twice
to do the same work and be able to have
the myars um you know dated differently.
Um but I'm trying to preserve taxpayer
revenue here. So um I is there any legal
reason why we can't do a date certain on
the annexation?
>> No. Uh madam chairwoman Dr. Aldrich. No,
the concern is that you would create two
effective dates in one ordinance. And I
don't know if the statute contemplates
that approach under these circumstances.
>> If we were to break out four and seven
separately into a separate ordinance,
would we be able to use the same uh in
uh surveying and myars or um I guess
we're going to have to redate the myars
anyway, but would we be able to use the
same surveying and but we would have to
renotice everything. Is that correct? Is
that my understanding correct?
>> Uh, I would defer to planning, but I I
would presume that it'll duplicate um a
lot of work. Um, but I would I would
defer to planning.
>> Thank you.
>> Um, Mr. Freddy, I do have a couple
questions. One, um, how does this work
with the 180day requirement?
Don't we have to have this done between,
isn't there 180 days in which we have to
begin and end the process?
I'm not aware of a statutory requirement
in that regard. Um, you know, maybe
planning department has an internal
policy, but I'm not aware of a legal
requirement.
>> I might have misread that. Um, and then
my second question is
um if we don't if we were to go forward
with Dr. Aldrich's
um
amendment,
is it legal to not go through the same
process again? I mean, are we not at
risk of violating someone's rights by
not doing the whole public notice and
the whole process all over again?
>> Madam Chairwoman, I I'm not sure I
understand the question. I I think you
know the concerns about a split
effective date aside um I don't see any
public notice concerns given that uh the
city has adhered to all those
requirements as part of each and each
individual parcel that's been part of
the ordinance that's currently before
you.
>> Okay Dr.
So follow up to your question, Madam
Chairwoman. If we are at third reading
now, if we postpone this
for your hypothetically, if we were to
postpone this for
certain length of time, pardon me. I
assume what the chairwoman was saying is
do we start the process all over again
or do we pick it up right where we are
at third reading?
I I think Madam Chairwoman, I I want to
make sure I'm clear there there's a
distinction between postponement and a
delayed effective date. So, um there's a
delayed effective date. I I don't see
concerns about um you know, the notice
requirements when it comes to the
annexation process. Um they've been
adhered to. The governing body
considered the annexation and adopted it
and set an effective date. State statute
clearly authorizes that. Um, now when it
comes to postponement, if you're
postponing for up to a year, I think
that creates um concerns
um both in the public and maybe from a
legal perspective that you know that
that initial notice that you may have
provided um sort of has had a shelf life
um and may no longer be um serving the
the purpose for which it was required.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> one more question. This isn't related to
what we're just discussing, but it was
brought up, I guess, from my own
understanding, it was um
violations of municipal code, whether it
be zoning or whatever portion of
municipal code have always been
um misdemeanor infractions and not
criminal penalties. Correct,
>> Madam Chairwoman? Yeah, I never maybe I
didn't know.
>> But by statute, all ordinances are
enforceable through a criminal penalty.
Uh the maximum of which is $750, 6
months in jail or both. Now that
>> then how do we determine but zoning
I mean I've always thought a zoning
violation would be a civil penalty and
not well criminal in the fact that the
misdemeanor allows you to jail somebody
if the judge wanted to do that.
>> Right. So I I and again I I'd welcome
planning if they'd like to speak on
this. I mean really what the city tries
to do and you know really the underlying
policy of all criminal law is is you
know compliance, right? Um so the the
policy of the city when it comes to
zoning and things of that nature is to
simply work with these property owners
to try and bring them into compliance.
You know, ultimately when the rubber
hits the road and you have a property
owner or somebody that um is unwilling
um to to meet the legal obligations that
they have, um that matter gets referred
to the city attorney's office and really
the only tool we have is prosecution um
as a criminal matter, but it's only a
misdemeanor, but you're correct. Yeah.
>> Okay. Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Chairwoman Emmens. Um I just want to
uh clarify my understanding is if we
were to postpone something that we can
only postpone it um till the next
meeting of the body which is basically
two weeks. Correct. And so we would have
to be doing that multiple times which I
think
I would just say I think that's unfair
to the family. I think that's unfair to
the business owners to not have some
sort of um certainty or some sort of um
time frame where they're having to feel
like they have to show up at our
meetings every two weeks and for and you
know ad nauseium until we can get all of
this cottified the fence fixed and make
sure that all the questions that they
have now that they have received the
answers and now have um consequential
questions answered. So I I would
encourage my colleagues to really
heavily consider that this is not a
postponement issue. This is a uh
separate date certain issue.
>> Madam Chairman, I I I wouldn't disagree.
I I guess just from from my office's
perspective, if if the policy that the
committee and that the governing body
wants to pursue is a delayed effective
date, that that policy be applied to the
entire ordinance and not to specific
parcels within the ordinance.
Dr. Renie, did you
>> No, I actually called myself out of
order question
>> on the amendment. Okay.
Okay. So, we have an amendment on the
floor. Oh, sorry, Dr. Mr. Leborn, you
can be documented.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Chairwoman,
I uh speak against this amendment,
not because I think the intent is wrong,
but because the complexities of the
matter obviously
um stretch this entire matter out
further, much further. And what I don't
understand about this amendment is
what'll happen in that year, who will be
doing what evaluation,
how that'll be reported,
how it conceivably in my mind could be
negotiated.
Um, which probably, uh,
under other circumstances could, uh,
be a reasonable idea.
Okay. Go ahead.
>> So,
if I may, I'd like to go on and really
point out
that
this is a unique circumstance
as demonstrated by the fact that we've
done
many many annexations of county pockets.
Um, I supported that and believe in it
because of my experience.
uh is really essential that over time
you have the ability to bring those
properties up to code and into the city
uh when those circumstances change. So,
it's it's really a long long-term
process that uh wasn't done many years
ago and that leaving it as it was
resulted in numerous cases of people
having to submit funds in escrow for
improvements to their street or their
property. And then the years went by and
we had and we rightly refunded it. So,
it got to the point where how can we do
this in the most equitable way, not only
for the people who have the county
pockets, but the people that live next
door to them.
How do we how do we make that city
standard universal? Well, it's probably
never going to be perfect,
but this is where we came to a situation
that we certainly I never uh conceived
of. It's um and one that uh as I've
stated has a lot of considerations that
go far beyond the responsibilities of
the city of Cheyenne when we're talking
about food and certainly the laws that
have changed lately in this regard.
So I just can't understand and I I think
it need would need to be well understood
what would happen in that year.
Um perhaps a shorter time frame with
some sort of form to that uh discussion
or negotiation would be appropriate.
And certainly I think that uh it's clear
that from what I can see that
the city attorney's office has brought
forward some concerns that
are unique to this situation. And I
can't recall ever trying to uh split
anything like this this way. Um
it might seem reasonable to the general
public, but legally it has some issues
here. And I do notice that uh
the farm has hired an attorney and is
evidently going to proceed to review the
legalities of it and possibly in court,
I guess.
But I really think that as difficult as
this situation is
and as unexpected as it was,
the uh planning office has brought
forward
our the documentation
that compares the county to the city
that looks at uh how this would fit into
our code and how it could be eventually
adopted and brought forward uh with the
rest of the UDC, which I believe I've
mentioned before, Madam Chairman,
I'd sure like to see this ability
be applied and be ready to be applied in
a variety of situations. I mean, maybe
other people have um I know there are
parcels that we've annexed that
I would guess could possibly take
advantage of this. So, I think it's
better to proceed with what we what we
begun here. I think that uh we've still
got a week before the final vote and I
don't understand how um
this whole controversy has gotten to the
point that there's so much
misunderstanding.
uh perhaps it's just as well to proceed
and see where we go from there because I
want to emphasize
when
this fear strikes and this discussion
becomes this cloud of dust or storm or
whatever you want to call it and you
start talking about imminent domain as a
condemnation as something that we would
consider
it's really not uh not right. There's no
such intent. I would like to see uh this
farm succeed if possible. Um I know it's
unique circumstances, but really
considering all that's gone into it, I
believe the time has come to proceed and
if we have to go to court about it, I
guess we do. But uh I really don't see
how this one year without a direct
explainable process is a benefit. It is
just kicking the can down the road for a
year. Maybe maybe we'll know more, but I
haven't heard that in the actual uh
amendment itself. So I'm in favor of uh
passing this on to the full council in
that final decision Monday, next Monday
night. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Dr. Aldrich. Um, Councilwoman
Emmens, I just would um I I just would
call for a vote on the amendment. I do
believe that we may have found another
way to postpone with date certain. Um,
and so we're going to pursue that.
>> Okay. All right. Um, so everyone in
favor of the amendment, please signify.
Vote I to signify. Yes. I
>> and those opposing.
Okay. So, that amendment fails. So,
we're back on
the resolution
ordinance. I'm sorry. So, are we ready
for a vote? All right. Everyone in favor
of the ordinance, uh, signify by saying
I.
>> Those opposed?
>> Absolutely. No.
>> Okay. So um the recommendation for the
public service committee will be to
adopt at the next meeting on Monday.
Number 11, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classifications of AG,
agricultural,
MR, medium density residential, CB
community business, and LI light
industrial for land annex to the city of
Cheyenne, generally located east of I25,
south of the intersection of Westland
Road and Missile Drive, north of West
and East Allison Road, and east and east
of and adjacent to North College Drive.
>> Staff report. I'll make this very quick.
I believe we've discussed most of this
already. Um, with any annexation, there
is the assigned zoning aspect. So, this
is just giving those annex properties a
city zone when they come into the city.
Uh, it is on third reading as well. And
I have no further updates.
>> Any questions?
>> All right, we'll go out to public
comment.
Is there any public comment in the room?
Hi, my name is Casey Hobble. Um, I own
the third most southern part part of
partial 7.
And I'm what I'm not understanding is
especially with zoning, if group seven
is one zone, how are you going to zone
that different if we can't
split it up to vote on something?
So if they're going to be zoned light
industrial, I live there. They don't.
How how is that going to affect me? Cuz
then I won't be in city code cuz I have
horses. You guys didn't even know we had
horses because you didn't do research
before you started the whole program
until we
voiced our opinion saying, "Hey, we got
horses, too. So, we're not unlike the
farm."
I don't I still don't
quite concerned on how this is going to
proceed.
and proceeding without knowing things.
It's kind of like jumping off a cliff
because everybody else doesn't. You
don't know what's going to happen. But
so why do we have to push to move
forward if we don't know what's going on
yet?
This is a unique situation for everyone.
So why don't we take our time and not
push? But
I don't know what the agenda is. So, I
don't know what you guys want out of
this. I don't understand anything. I'm
just a simple country boy that works his
ass off for what he has.
And now it could get ripped away cuz we
don't even know how to zone anything.
So,
I just beg that we at least zone us
correctly cuz otherwise everything I
have is gone.
Thank you.
>> Dr. Renie, did you want
>> Madam Chairwoman? If I look at the map
that's been provided to us, and I don't
know what the page is, but the two
parcels to the north that Mr. Hobble was
referring to are zoned all. His parcel
is zoned AG.
>> Um, Mr. Hubble, I would ask you to get
with the planning folks and they will be
able to help explain the specifics.
I can
>> go ahead Conor.
>> Madam Chair, Connor, Planning and
Development Department. I'm more than
happy to also just um explain this and
bring some clarity as well. Um in the
ordinance itself, I did split parcel
basically what is considered parcel 7 or
pocket 7 into A and B. Um I do have a
legal description. Basically, the two
parcels to the north are technically
platted and have a very easy legal
description. And then um Mr. Hubble's
par parcel uh has a longer legal
description because it's considered
unplatted land or by the county's
definition. Um and that is separated out
so that we can actually specifically
zone the two parcels to the north LI and
then their property AG. Um so that is
possible with the zoning and that is
what is being proposed even with that
ordinance.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> that was my question. You kept Mr. White
kept saying it was possible, but I want
to confirm that that's
>> what's actually there. That's what I
read on my
>> madam chair through you. It is possible
for us to do it and we that's what we
are proposing. Yep. So that is in the
ordinance. That's how we're proposing
it. That's how it was brought to
planning commission and before you is to
separate those.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> Mr. All right. So, with that AG zoning
on that third part of that
parcel, um, won't these people be able
to keep their horses?
>> Madam Chair, through you. Yes. So,
they'd be under the agricultural zone
similar to the Nicely where it would
fall into one of those either general
agriculture or limited agriculture which
allows for farm animals or horses,
livestock, and allows basically
expansion of that.
Connor, will you give your card to Mr.
Hubble to make sure that he has a way of
getting a hold of you for questions?
>> Dr. Aldridge, Councilwoman,
I just want to be very clear about this
that that right now again the urban farm
and those designations are only in
policy. They are not codified. So we
that is something we're working towards
codifying, but it is not currently
codified. Madam Chair, through you. The
three definitions at the top, general,
limited, and agricultural product sales
are all codified within the UDC. Those
are the three land uses that we
currently have in the UDC.
Um that basically staff would review any
basically any use under
basically look at what the use is and it
would fall into one of those three. So
>> the urban use definition is our
department's take on basically giving
that sort of use kind of its
interpretation.
>> So Connor would general agriculture not
protect them in order to keep their
horses.
>> Madam chair through you it would general
agricultural limited agricultural they
would fall into one of those two
categories. Again, with agricultural
uses in an agricultural zone, you are
allowed to have livestock, horses, cows,
pigs, chickens, you're allowed to expand
those. You're allowed to increase your
number. You're in an agricultural zone.
That is what that zone is for. Those are
the uses that are currently in the UDC.
again with the interpretation for urban
farm that is trying to take those three
uses that are currently codified and
kind of interpret how would how that use
would be I think director Bloom tried to
even mention we don't have a definition
for churches in the UDC they follow
under general assembly or assembly one
of our assembly limited ones there is no
specific definition for churches but
when one comes in we have to look at the
uses that are in our use table and in
our definitions and figure out which use
it falls into. So that is how that sheet
works is that those are the three uses
on the top that are codified in the UDC
in our use table and have definitions
and then urban farm is our
interpretation of how urban farm
basically works with those three uses
and combines them into one.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Um, just for clarification, so and maybe
I misunderstood, but my understanding
was that the last sentence in
agriculture product sales/farmers market
is not part has not been codified. And
at the top it says, "This document
provides for clarification regarding
urban farm as it relates to and
supplements the following existing
agriculture uses definitions of unified
development code subsection for 1.4.4h
and the definitions as amended in the
future." So, are these definitions
actually the definitions that are in the
code currently or are they what we're
hoping to amend in the future?
>> Madam Chair, through you. Those are the
definitions currently in the UDC that
could be amended in the future to
actually
bring forward something that would help
with the actual definition for an urban
farm.
>> But those definitions are actually, if
you go into the UDC right now, are
actually in the code.
>> Okay. Any other public comments?
>> Mr. Brody.
>> Madam Chairman, I just wanted to offer
one maybe point of clarification beyond
beyond the city's zoning regulations and
the protections um that are I guess
necessarily implied as part of an a
zoning. Um state statute also has
protections for folks that are getting
annexed. So any historical uses um that
these folks may have on their property,
as long as those are cataloged and
recorded with the city, regardless of
the zone, they get to keep that. Um it's
just that the use has to continue into
um you know on yearly uh cycles of use
to keep it alive, so to speak. So I just
wanted to say there's more protections
other than just the zoning code. So just
for clarity, if they have horses now,
they would be able to continue to have
horses in the future as long,
>> sorry,
>> as long as they continue to do that.
>> Correct. Under that statutory
protection, which I think is 151410.
>> Thank you.
>> It is.
>> Okay. Other public comment, Mr. Nicely.
>> Yeah, David Nicely again. Um, at the
beginning of this process, um,
it it was stated at the planning
commission that we agreed with the AG
zoning
and I stood up and objected to the
agreement with the AG zoning
only because having been given
a week's notice that the process was
going on that I didn't know what I
thought the zoning should be.
Now, that was on the first 2nd of
February. Now, we're at the 2nd of
March, if I'm right, a month later, I
still don't know what the zoning could
be or should be. Um, and we're still
talking about fixing it, and we haven't
settled on how we're going to fix it
because it's an incredibly complex
matter. Um,
you know, Mr. Bloom um and I appreciate
his work said that they're trying to
make it easy for us. Well, it's not
easy. It would have been a heck of a lot
easier. Forgive me. Um it would have
been a lot easier if three and a half
years ago when I approached planning and
said, "This is what we're doing.
You want to annex us? Eventually, you're
going to come to annex us. This is what
we're doing." if they'd have listened
and planned for it and asked questions
about what we're doing. This would have
been easier if in December when I was
emailing city council members and
calling them if they would have answered
them and asked the questions. This would
have been easier if on January 28th when
I was sending out multiple emails to the
mayor and to city council members and to
city staff if they would have answered.
But nobody answered. They wouldn't
return calls. They wouldn't answer
emails. Nobody answered until a viral
Facebook posts got to 200,000
views. Um, you've got a problem. You
know, Dr. Renie, you you said if one
person stands up and and expresses a
concern, there's probably a whole lot
more. Well, there's a lot of people that
just doesn't trust
the city.
I've had 15 years of bad experience with
the city. You've been bad neighbors.
I'll take my chances with the county.
Um, nobody's kind, empathetic. Nobody
wants to hear the stories. Nobody's
asked.
I don't know what the right answer is
with respect to zoning.
You don't know the right answer with
respect to zoning, respectfully. Um, but
let's barrel forward for reasons
unstated. Let's just go forward and see
where we go. Um, I'm frustrated with the
whole thing. I'm frustrated with most of
y'all. Um,
why can't we just go back to Mayberry?
>> Mr. Nicely. I'm sorry, but you're out of
time.
>> Out of time. Sure.
>> Okay, we have Is there any other public
comment? Is there any online, Jennifer?
Oh, I'm sorry.
My name's Roxy Havvel and I'm owner of
Track 7, the southern part. I just
wanted to clarify my husband's comment.
Um, it is proposed to you guys that you
act or zone us agg. It's not in writing
that we are going to be zoned agged. We
are worried you guys sit here say you
can't split our parcels, but then you're
going to split our parcels to zone us
different. It's no guaranteed. We don't
know. We have to trust the system that
you guys are going to do what is right
when you didn't even know until February
2nd that we actually owned animals and
our dreams to do with this property. So
to clarify, I just want you guys to know
he wasn't saying that we didn't know the
understanding. We had a meeting with the
mayor, but we feel that we are being
lied to to be told what we're need to be
told so that we will agree to this
situation. We don't know what is
actually going to happen. as being
clarified right now. You guys don't even
know the actual meaning of all of this.
So, I just wanted to clarify my
husband's statement that we do know that
we want to be zoned agg, but it's
proposed to you guys that you will
actually come through with us that. So,
thank you.
>> Thank you.
So, we have the amendment which does
I'm sorry, the ordinance which does
identify all of the zoning right now on
third reading. Um, do we have a motion?
>> I would so move.
>> Second.
>> So, moved by Dr. Aldridge, seconded by
Dr. Renie. Any comments? Madam
>> Chairwoman, I have a couple questions
for staff.
>> Dr. Renie.
So,
um, through you, Madam Chairwoman, to
Mr. White. One,
obviously, we know what the zone for
that lower part of parcel 7 is going to
be because that's on the map in front of
us that's presented to us. Correct,
>> Madam Chair, through you. Yes. It's also
what's really codifying it though is the
ordinance. The ordinance specifies that
what I have delineated as 7B which is
that specific parcel
>> will go from LU county to AG in the
city.
>> Okay.
Had it been in LA in the county before?
>> Uh Madam Chair through you? No, actually
it was I think A1 or A2 prior to the
county's resoning. So it's
>> it was AG prior to the county's
resoning.
>> Okay. Sorry, I misheard then. So we're
matching the county zone. So, um, Madam
Chairman, again to Mr. White,
if I recall in our process over the last
couple years of doing this, we annexed
somebody on the north side of town that
had horses
and I assume their horses are still
there to the best of our knowledge. Is
that
>> Madam Chair through those to the best of
my knowledge? I believe I'd have to look
at our map. That one was a while ago,
but I believe we resoneed them either
agricultural, residential, or
agricultural. So, AG, one of the two
agricultural zones, which again allows
for horses and I believe they are still
there. We they haven't contacted us. So,
>> as far as we know, we still have their
horses. We also zoned some or annexed
somebody that had a a home occupation
business. It was like truckking related
or something.
>> Madam Chair, through
>> as far as I know, that's as far as we
know, that's still there. Correct.
>> Madam Chair, through you. So far, when
it comes to any of the county pocket
annexations and the zones we've
assigned, whether they had a
non-conforming use or conforming use or
these home occupations that were allowed
in the county, we've allowed all those
to continue. Um, I've had no phone calls
from anybody who's been previously
annexed um that had an issue with uh
their business not being allowed any
longer. Um, I've maybe had one phone
call from somebody who wasn't too
thrilled after the fact, but that was a
water and sewer thing. Um, but other
than like any comments about not being
allowed to do their businesses or keep
using their property as is, I've had no
phone calls.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
>> Any other comments from the council? All
right, then we're going to call for a
vote. Um, all those in favor of the
ordinance, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And opposed.
So that uh the recommendation for the
public service committee will be to
adopt
um the or approve the ordinance going
forward the next meeting. Okay. Number
14 resolution authorizing the mayor and
city clerk to sign a final plat for
village cooperative city of Cheyenne
Larry County Wyoming located north of
Prairie Avenue east of Powder House Road
west of Rutair and south of Story
Boulevard.
Hey
Madame Chair, Morgan Dennis, Planning
and Development. Um, this is the plat
that's following the zone change. Um,
there is an exception to this plat. It
takes place on an oversized block which
requires some sort of easement. Um,
there is an extension of
Melton Street that has been added to
this plat that satisfies that exception.
Um, this has been postponed because the
zone change and the plat need to be
approved at the same time. Um, there
have been no comments or changes, so I
stand for questions.
>> Are there any questions for staff?
All right. Do we have any public comment
in the room?
Any public comment online?
Okay.
Do we have questions from the comm or
I'm sorry, is there a motion from the
council?
>> Second.
>> Okay. We have a first from Dr. Renie and
um seconded from Dr. Aldridge. Any
questions or comments?
Okay. All those in favor, please signify
by I I
>> I.
>> Uh those opposed.
Okay. So the recommendation for the p uh
the recommendation from the public
service committee will be to adopt at
the next meeting of the governing body.
And with that our business is completed.
Thank you. See?